Hello class.
So today we're going
to be looking at the
lymphatic system,
continuing our more general
discussion of fluids
that I started with you
in the intro to cranial
with Dr. Sutherland's
concept of fluid
fluctuation in the CSF.
So we'll look at the lymph
system, you know, looking
at the later objectives
we'll be looking at the
mechanics of it the
physiology of it how you go
about diagnosing and treating
it but first we'll be
looking at its role in
particularly in inflammation
and how it functions in
the interstitial space so
we'll start with a thought
from Dr. Sutherland
and it's a little bit of
a different thought I know
very often we think of
OMM as, you know, taking
tight spots and making
them loose or stiff spots.
But here he's saying,
well, the goal of an
osteopathic treatment isn't
necessarily so much to
look at tissue tension,
but ultimately to affect
a more efficient
interchange between all the
fluids of the body across
all of its interfaces.
And now that may seem like
a really daunting thing to
do, but actually we only
have three different, you
know, contained bodies of
fluid to affect interchange.
They would be the largest,
the intracellular fluid, the
smallest, the intravascular
fluid, and then the
extravascular, extracellular
fluid, or interstitial fluid.
And as you can see, when
we're looking at exchange,
the exchange always involves
the interstitium. And
so that concept of affecting
an efficient interchange
of fluid brings us to a
study of the interstitial
space almost as its
own organ system where
you can see all of the
cells of our body float in
the interstitial space.
And so exchange with the
cells is going to occur in
relation to the interstitium
as well as exchange in
the vascular system.
And as we study the lymph
system will be looking
at its role in that
process, but starting with a
really important thought
about the interstitium.
You know, when I was in
school and studying, it was
either stated or simply
implied that the heart was at
the root of not just
circulation, which would be the
movement through the vascular
system, but everything
that would occur after
capillary filtration. So the
heart would bring fluid
down to the capillaries, a
pressure gradient would push
it across, that pressure
gradient would continue to
move it through where it
would exit either into the
lymph or into the venous
system. And so the exchange
would occur as a response
to this, that the pressure
gradient from the heart
would actually move the
fluid through, maintaining
concentration gradients for
exchange with all the cells.
That was proven untrue when
they, that was actually
developed from a faulty
technology that left the
belief that interstitial
pressure was positive and
that there was a continuous
pressure gradient
from the heart through the
capillaries and across.
When they actually developed
the proper technology
to truly measure interstitial
pressure, they found
it to be negative. So with
the negative interstitial
pressure then, that
pressure gradient from the
heart does not account for
any movement of interstitial
fluid except across
that capillary barrier.
And whatever occurs to
maintain concentration
gradients would have to be
separate, a separate sort
of physiology. And then
when they got in and
measured pressure in that
initial lymphatic capillary,
it was also negative,
but it was less negative
than the pressure in the
interstitium. So ultimately,
even though it seems
like a double negative,
you actually have an uphill
positive pressure gradient
to move fluid from the
interstitium into the lymph.
And so most of the
study that was done
didn't really have
to do with what's
facilitating cellular
exchange. It was,
well, how is this fluid
moving into the lymphatic
then? And so our study
of lymph is actually
going to take us to the
forces that are actually
working in the interstitium,
a separate mechanism
from our circulatory
system, what I've called
here an interstitial
mechanism that promotes
interchange and facilitates
cellular respiration.
exchange of oxygen and
waste disposal of carbon
dioxide, the absorption
of nutrients, the disposal
of waste products.
And when you look at a
mechanism in a body of fluid,
then the laws of inertia
become really significant.
So if I'm moving
something on a solid
surface, I have a desk on the
floor. If I push that desk
12 inches, it moves 12
inches. As soon as I stop
pushing it, it stops.
Whereas inertia would
say, once a body's
in motion, it
remains in motion. So
now let's take that
desk and make it
a boat, and we'll
put it in the lake.
And if I push that boat
a foot in the lake,
because I want to get that
boat out into the water
where I can jump into
it and not hit bottom.
Well, if I push that
boat out a foot, that
boat's going to keep
going because now the
laws of inertia work
much more effectively.
And pretty soon that boat's
going to be so far out,
I'm not going to be able to
get out there and get into
it unless I swim to it.
And so once you're working
in a body of water, which
the interstitial fluid can
be considered, you know, a
body of water, then the laws
of inertia take place, which
is a good thing. Because
that interstitial mechanism
in our body, once it
gets going, well, it'll
keep going, because of the
laws of inertia. And that
is something that is true
through almost all of our
lives while we're healthy. But
remember also that inertia
says that a body at rest
will remain at rest. And
so if that interstitial
mechanism becomes static, that
can become a major problem
for our body and something
I think that goes straight
to the heart of osteopathic
theory and something
that we need to consider in
our osteopathic practices.
So that's the
background for this.
The lymph is tied to that
interstitial mechanism
all the way to the point
where its development
occurs in response to
it. So this is from an
embryologist named Blechschmidt,
who did some really
remarkable studies. And
what he said was that what
actually causes a lymphatic
vessel to develop is
interstitial fluid
communicate. In other words,
once you establish
interstitial fluid flow, then
you start to see the
development of lymph vessels.
So that interstitial
mechanism, that
movement of the
interstitial fluid, is
actually what's causing
lymph to develop.
Lymph also have shown a
remarkable ability
to regenerate.
And some, you know,
50 years later, the
researchers who studied
lymph regeneration,
what they're calling
lymphangiogenesis, found exactly
the same thing, a tissue
response to interstitial fluid
flow. And so the relationship
of the lymph system to
the interstitium is very
fundamental, and they work off
the same forces in that
same interstitial mechanism.
and so I'd like to present
the lymph system to you and
you know most times when
we study it in school we
see this, we see the lymph
system draining back into
the venous system and we
think oh the lymph is a part
of the circulatory system
but really the lymph unlike
the circulatory system is
open to the interstitium in
fact if you look at the
fluid in the interstitium and
the fluid in that initial
lymph capillary they're
exactly the same so that most
of the researchers who do
this study actually call
interstitial fluid lymph
because it's really the same
fluid and the lymphatic is
open to the interstitium
and really functions as part
of that rather than part
of the circulatory system
it just is an organ system
that will ultimately drain
back into the circulatory
system. And so that's how
I'm going to be presenting
it to you in this talk.
Now, as we look at the
role of the lymphatics,
I'd like to just take a moment
and look at the importance
of osmolarity because
the lymph are involved in
helping keep osmolar balance
in the interstitium. And
so here's our perfect
little cell. And if we put
that perfect little cell in
an interstitium with a perfect
osmolar content, it stays
a perfect little cell.
But if we put it into a
hypo or hyperosmolar fluid,
well, look what happens to
that cell. It becomes so
distorted, it becomes non
-functional. And so maintaining
osmolar balance is
critical to our physiology.
And the lymph
are, in many ways,
integral to that
because of protein.
So here's our vessel. And
what we'll see is that that
vessel is absolutely loaded
with protein, whereas
our interstitium should be
essentially devoid of it.
and but as they tend to
teach us 10% of our protein
will leak into the interstitium
now the capillary the
cells that make up the
capillary the endothelium have
have tight junctions so
theoretically they should
not be allowing protein to
pass but somehow 10% of that
protein gets out But once
it gets out, it can't get
back into the capillary.
So any protein that leaks
out into the interstitium,
which would create a
hyperosmolar interstitium, has
to be drained by the lymph.
And the lymph being open
to the interstitium is open
to any of those large
particles, proteins, big
particles, debris, cells,
etc. They can all pass through
into the lymph. uh and um
so I've I've spent a lot
of time thinking about this
and um the idea that somehow
our bodies are designed
with leaky pipes uh didn't
make any sense to me so
um how does protein leak
out of this vessel that's
supposed to uh have competent
tight junctions uh and the
answer is inflammation,
which to some degree is
occurring. You know, it
occurs at our skin in
response to its interaction
with the external
environment. The inside of
our gut tube also is an
external environment.
There's going to be some
level of inflammation in
response to that, and in
our lungs the same way,
you know, there's low
levels of inflammation,
not where you'd call
it an inflammatory
process, more like
our body's response.
That's going to
change the capillary
barrier, allow some of
that protein to leak.
But that becomes
dramatically altered with
inflammation. And so in
inflammation, there's
a major change in
capillary permeability.
Proteins pour out.
And so the lymphatics become
hugely important in the
body's management of
inflammation, in part because
of that. So to look at the
functional role, lymphatics
play a role in normal
physiology, but they have
a really outsized role in
inflammation. So we can
start with the obvious, you
know, the lymphatics are
going to carry antigen to
the lymph nodes and are
therefore deeply involved
in the generation of an
immune response. something
you'll see in infections.
But the circulatory
considerations in inflammation,
I think, are arguably
an even more important
role. And so, again, when
you have inflammation,
you change capillary
permeability. There's
all this protein
inside the vasculature,
theoretically, none
in the interstitium.
And all of a sudden,
that huge amount of
protein pours out into
the interstitium. That's
actually why we swell
with inflammation.
It's not because of a pressure
gradient, it's because
of an osmotic gradient. And
so the fluid actually is
following the protein, making
it an exudate, as opposed
to heart failure, where it's
just a pressure gradient,
and that's just water coming
out into the interstitium.
This is a very high protein
fluid. And what's interesting
is they've shown that
no matter what you do to
capillary permeability,
because there's so much protein
in the vasculature, there's
always going to be an efflux
of protein. And so you can't
drain that protein back
into the capillary. Any
amount you drained is going
to be more than matched by
more coming in. and so the
lymph is the only way to
drain that exudate out and so
it becomes critical to
circulation during inflammation
and remember that as you
swell that pressure of the
interstitium is going to
go up capillary filtration
pressure is very very small
so before long all of a
sudden you raise pressure
just enough that you no
longer have a gradient for
any kind of fluid coming in
and the only way to get
more fluid in is through
draining some out some of
what's there so in that scenario
you know you want to give
someone meds and we we
tend to think well if I can
get the medicine into the
blood it's automatically
delivered but if I don't
really have a good capillary
filtration pressure here,
that medicine is going to
go everywhere in the body
except this inflamed area
where I need to get it,
whether that's an antibiotic
or an anti-inflammatory
or whatever medicine that
it is. And the only way to
get more fluid in is through
drainage. And so lymph
then becomes central to both
sides of the circulation,
not just drainage, but
supply. And it's critical.
And I don't think we think
that. Again, the idea
of the interstitium as
just an extension of the
circulatory system or
something that's automatic is
naive and not really
consistent with physiology.
And that's something that
Dr. Still seemed attuned
to, even though most of
this information came
forward 100 years later.
where he's saying, you know,
disease is too much dirt
in the wheels of life.
Then he's talking about
lymphatics. Nature
takes this method to
wash out the dirt.
Pneumonia is too
much dirt in the
wheels of the lungs.
And interestingly,
you know, the idea
of lymph being
necessary to bring fluid in.
Nowhere can we go to a
better place for water than
to the lymphatics, seemingly
right on target there.
So, and then to take
this one step further,
looking again at inflammation
and how it resolves,
and did lymph play
a role in that? And
actually, the lymph are
absolutely critical to the
progression and resolution
of inflammation.
And when you look at some
of the research, and I'll
kind of give you the tip of
the iceberg with research,
I've given you some
references at the end, but
going through the research
on this would be a whole
other hour lecture. so
I'm going to kind of bust
through it. But so many
acute and chronic diseases,
particularly chronic
inflammatory diseases, chronic
fibrotic diseases, and the
idea of fibrotic diseases
brings up this notion of
inflammation not as an event.
You know, we tend to think,
you know, I turn my ankle,
it swells up and gets
inflamed, I have inflammation,
I need to stop it. And we
use anti-inflammatories.
But they've done some
studies that actually, if you
use anti-inflammatories too
much in sprained ankles,
you dramatically increase
the probability of getting
a chronic ankle sprain
because it doesn't heal right.
And inflammation isn't
an event that starts and
stops in response to an
injury. It's a process.
And the early part of
the process is acute
inflammation that we know.
There's swelling, there's,
you know, we bring in
macrophages and neutrophils,
we kill the bad guys,
we make a big mess.
But then inflammation also
includes proliferative
phase, which is when we're
activating fibroblasts
and rebuilding tissue. And
then finally that resolves,
then truly the full process
is over and everything
comes back to normal. So
what drives this process
are not just the cells,
but a large and growing
group of chemicals. so
that in acute inflammation,
I have chemicals that draw
in the macrophages and
neutrophils trigger them to
act, activate the nervous
system, activate all
different kinds of systems,
activate the pain receptors.
And I have acute inflammation
driven by a group of chemicals.
Now, as I drain those
chemicals and the situation
starts to evolve, as
those drain, now I can
bring in chemicals that
don't necessarily bring
in the macrophages and
neutrophils. They activate
the fibroblasts. And
it's a different set of
chemicals, but it's part
of the same process.
And those chemicals will
drive proliferation. and I
rebuild my tissue. And then
as I drain those chemicals
and stop activating the
fibroblast, everything
returns to normal. Now, if
my lymphatic system obstructs
here, or if the body just
gets stuck in that acute
inflammation, well, then I
have a chronic inflammatory
process, whether it's,
you know, a chronically
sprained ankle or a rheumatic
joint that just doesn't
quiet down, an infection
that smolders and doesn't
really resolve, if I get
past here and I get into my
proliferative phase and I
stop here and I get stuck,
now I have proliferative
diseases and almost any
fibrotic disease in the
body can be tied to impaired
lymphatic drainage that stops
the proliferative process
or that maintains the
proliferative process and
doesn't allow it to
resolve. So everything from
interstitial lung disease to
post-operative adhesions to
any of the sort of
scarring diseases. And
all of these diseases
have been tied to
impaired lymphatic drainage
because it's lymphatic
drainage that drives
this progression.
And effective lymphatic
drainage that allows this, you
know, the healthiest thing
is not to limit or eliminate
inflammation. The healthiest
thing is to help the
body get through it quickly
and efficiently and go
from acute inflammation to
proliferation to resolution.
And that'll give us the best
response and the best healing.
And that's something that
really can't be done medically.
actually. The lymph
system, there is no
medical or pharmaceutical
management for
the lymph system, so
it's really up to us.
So that idea that those
inflammatory mediators that
are really driving this
whole process are broken down
after they're brought back
to the systemic circulation
by lymph drainage. And that
whole process of inflammation,
proliferation, and healing
is really dependent on
the lymph system. And that's,
in my mind, why it's so
important. The cells, even
of acute inflammation,
they're also going to be
removed through lymph drainage.
And so, again, all of
this came out 100 years
after Dr. Still gave us
his theory that says,
again, talking about the lymph,
it behooves us to
handle them with care.
For by them and from
them, a withered limb,
organ, or division of
the body receives what we
call reconstruction or
is builded anew. Again,
right on target there
and way ahead of
any of the medical
thinkers of his time. So
a brief look at the
research. Again, I
did leave you some
references at the end.
And research can be divided
into three categories.
What happens to a normal tissue
when you take out the lymph?
What happens to the lymph
in diseases? The obvious
one, like the one I'll refer
to is Crohn's. When you
get to the point of surgery
for Crohn's, you can look
at the lymph that are
draining the diseased tissue.
And then you give
a tissue disease.
They gave, I think,
sheep heart attacks,
and half of them had
lymph and half of
them didn't. And what
happened to them?
And the results are striking in
both acute and chronic disease.
And again, I really can't
go through this. You
know, the pulmonary
stuff, I'm going to give
you pulmonary lectures.
So we'll look at the
role of the lymph and
asthma and pneumonia,
even COVID. When our patients
died from COVID, they
died from inflammation,
overwhelming inflammation.
In the heart, you know,
if you cut the lymph and
give an animal a heart attack,
you get larger MIs that
spread after that initial
MI. You get more arrhythmias.
I mean, the whole situation
becomes much worse.
In the gut, you can go
from transient elevation
of pancreatic enzymes to
fulminant, life-threatening
pancreatitis.
You know, think about
a ruptured appendix and
peritonitis and big
inflammatory processes.
And we'll be looking at
inflammatory bowel disease
as well. And then
chronically, if you just cut
the lymph and see what
happens to an organ, you
basically get fibrotic
disease in almost any organ.
Interstitial fibrosis in
the lungs, that looks like
the interstitial disease
in the lung. In the heart,
you can actually produce
fibrosis that produce valve
disease that looks like
sort of typical mitral valve
disease that occurs with
aging, you know, a thickened
myocardium that loses
its stroke volume, again,
almost like an age-related
change in the heart, and
you can produce atherosclerosis
in the cardiovascular
system. Interestingly,
in the gut tube, if you
just remove lymph from a
normal animal, it'll actually
produce Crohn's lesions,
which is pretty striking,
showing that relation. So
I'd like to try and build
you a model of the lymphatic
system in health and
disease. And I'll use a
couple of lines of research.
One was the research into
post-mastectomy, right?
So after mastectomy, some
women get lymphedema,
particularly if you've done
an axillary node dissection.
So instead of asking,
why do some women get
lymphedema after
they've had an axillary
dissection? I mean,
essentially, you've
eliminated the lymph
drainage pathway entirely.
So a more appropriate
question might be, why
doesn't every woman get
lymphedema immediately?
And most times, it's
rare to go home from the
hospital after a
mastectomy with lymphedema.
Usually, it'll occur six
or nine months later.
So they tried to study it,
and they used dogs. And
what they did was they took
the thigh, and they dissected
out everything, but in
like a one-inch swath,
circumferentially dissecting
everything but the femur.
the femoral artery, the
femoral nerve, and the femoral
vein, thinking, okay,
now we've eliminated any
possibility of lymph drainage,
we should be fine. But they
put a skin flap on to
keep the tissue alive, and
those dogs never got lymphedema.
And when they looked,
they actually found that
enough lymph had regenerated
in that skin flap to basically
drain the entire leg.
but as those dogs went
on for about nine months
about nine months later all
of a sudden they started
all developing lymphedema
and when they went and
looked back they saw that
the the skin flaps had
had fibrosed enough that
that many of those lymphs
had fibrosed shut and
now there wasn't enough
lymph drainage, and now
you're all of a sudden getting
lymphedema. So remember
that lymph regenerate.
But as you have protein
in the interstitial
space, even just
protein without
any other mediators will
actually strongly stimulate
fibroblasts. So the more
protein you have in the
interstitium, the more you
activate fibroblasts. The
more lymph drainage you have,
the more you remove that
protein, the less you'll
drive fibrosis. And the
interstitial fluid movement
that's producing that will
actually cause more lymph
regeneration because
interstitial fluid is what
produces lymph regeneration.
And so I think this
is telling in terms
of how our body
works and how it can
get in trouble and
a balance between
lymph drainage, interstitial
fluid flux, and the kind
of constant drive for
tissue building, which will
ultimately lead to fibrosis,
and the constant drive to
lymph regeneration, which
will keep that clean and
reduce fibrosis, something
that we need to think about.
And then looking at how that
applies to a disease, it
was amazing. When they
just obstructed lymph in a
healthy animal, not an animal
that had Crohn's, they would
actually produce Crohn's
lesions. And then when they
looked at the mesenteries
of patients who had bowel
resections for their Crohn's
disease, in those mesenteries,
the lymphatics were all
obstructed by fibrosis.
And so they developed
a theory that,
you know, again,
looking at that balance,
because usually with
Crohn's, you know, it
shows up as a bellyache
and maybe some diarrhea.
And you have this mild
exacerbation that clears.
And then the next one you
have is a little more severe
and the next one more
severe until finally one so
severe that you get ulcers,
and then finally so severe
that those ulcers don't
heal, and now you have a
bowel resection. And so
the idea would be that each
successive attack, that
inflammation sets up a process
of fibrosis, and that progressive
fibrosis will ultimately
limit lymph drainage,
which will allow the next
attack to be worse because
the body can't manage it
as well because the inflammation
is managed until finally
you fibrose off those
lymph, you can't manage it
at all, and you need a bowel
resection. And so again,
this imbalance between
tissue building and lymph
regeneration And what is it
that causes lymph regeneration
to sort of counterbalance
that progressive fibrosis
from chronic inflammation?
And the answer is
interstitial fluid flow. That's
the drive. And so I think
that's important and I'd
like you to remember that
because that concept of an
interstitial mechanism that
promotes, that creates
lymph, that actually drives
fluid into the lymph and
also facilitates cellular
respiration and drives lymph
regeneration is so fundamental.
and it is something that
you can learn to sense.
And so that concept of
fluid fluctuation that
Dr. Sutherland brought
to us through his cranial
concept, I think is
something that's just
hugely important and
something that we need to
include in our overall
osteopathic thinking.
And then again, that
concept of reducing fluid
flux will simultaneously
reduce lymph drainage. I'm
going to look at how
fluid flux works with that
uphill gradient that I
talked about, getting
fluid into the lymph, so
actually producing lymph
and facilitating lymph
drainage. also lymph
regeneration and how limiting
that process will actually
promote fibrosis over
time and make ourselves
vulnerable, more vulnerable
to chronic disease.
And it is something that we can
have access to or
have influence on.
Again, from Dr. Still,
if this be true, we must
keep them normal all
the time or see confused
nature in the form of
disease the list through.
Thus, we strike at
the source of life
and death when we go
to the lymphatics.
So how does this lymph
system work, and how
can we evaluate it
and give a treatment?
Again, not so much designed
to relax tissues or
take away strain or help
somebody with a backache.
How can we tie into this
physiology and design a
treatment that improves it for
patients who really are sick
or have chronic inflammatory
diseases or acute
inflammatory diseases? So as
we look at the lymph system,
it can sort of arbitrarily be
divided into three separate
aspects of physiology.
You have that concept of
formation, which again is
not a passive process. Fluid
doesn't just pour into the
lymph. It actually has to be
pumped into the lymph because
there's an uphill pressure
gradient that you need to
overcome and no osmotic
gradient. So there needs to
be an external force there,
so that's one aspect. And
then once you get it into
the vessel, then you need to
pump it through the vessel
centrally, and then finally
get it to the thoracic
duct and ultimately drain
it into the subclavian vein.
As we look at that, we'll
look at it in reverse
because there's no reason
to try to get fluid
into the limb system if
the fluid can't get out
of the lymph system. So
in terms of designing
my treatment, then I'm
going to start here, then
my work my way through
here, and finally here.
So terminal lymph drainage
is part of a model that
was brought to us by Dr.
Zink. He was a DO who did most
of his writing anyway through
the 1970s and produced
what we now teach as the
respiratory circulatory
model that really came
from Dr. Zink. This is from
Dr. Zink. The treatment of
the lymph system must always
begin by securing terminal
drainage by way of ensuring
a good abdominal thoracic
venous pump. Venous
stasis may precede lymph
blockage, but it's the lymphatic
disturbance that spells
disaster to the tissues.
And again, this idea
that the heart only gets
fluid to the capillaries.
It doesn't get it through
the interstitium, and it
doesn't get it through
the venous or right
side of the circulation.
In fact, remember that
venous blood formation,
the movement of that
interstitial fluid
back into the venous
system is done by an
osmotic gradient, not
a pressure gradient.
And so what is it
that drives that
right side of the circulation?
That would be breathing.
And that not only is
breathing responsible
for venous circulation,
but it's also
responsible for
terminal lymph drainage.
This is something that
was studied in the 70s and
80s. And basically, somewhere
around half of thoracic
duct flows produced by
respiration. The thoracic
duct does have smooth muscle
that also participates.
There's a number of
things that contribute.
How does breathing affect?
Well, a lot of it is the
same thing as venous, that
suction pump, the negative
pressure in the thorax
that occurs when you
breathe. We'll also look
at the cisterna chile, the
beginning of the thoracic
duct, and the area of the
thoracic inlet as two
specific areas to look at. you
know, the big thing is
going to be the negative
inner thoracic pressure
that's going to act on venous
and lymphatic fluid as it
moves back to the heart.
But Dr. Sutherland drew a
very interesting analogy
between the thoracic
duct, which has a bulb on
the bottom, this is
sardachyle, and comes up over
the top and turns down,
sort of like the idea
of a siphon where you can
get fluid to move uphill
as long as it ultimately
goes downhill, as long
as you start it with a
pump squeezing this bulb.
And so that siphon
concept brings us to two
areas. at the top where
you can apply a little
suction at the top end of
that siphon to get things
moving. And there is
some suction that occurs
here. And also just to
look at this area and how
crowded it is. And easily
this is to congest.
And so working the
thoracic inlet, besides
its role in the overall
negative intrathoracic
pressure, which is
not the biggest, but
it's a critical area.
Dr. Zink always started
his lymph treatment
at the thoracic inlet.
And then down here where,
you know, that concept
of squeezing that bulb
of the siphon, and you
look at the cisterna
kylie, and you would think
if you wanted to just
allow that fluid to pass,
you'd put it in the
tendinous portion, right?
I mean, this is a very
thin vessel and how easy
that would be to get squeezed
under what's the largest
muscle here. And so Dr.
Sutherland brought up
the idea that there was
a physical pumping, like
squeezing that bulb. And
the reason you would put
it under this thick muscle
was because it acted as
a pump. And so making
sure the thoracic inlet is
open. Yes, freeing the
diaphragm as a whole, but
looking at the lumbar
spine in particular and the
upper lumbars and making
sure that the cruce is
moving and functioning so
that pump action is also.
And then ultimately that
sort of terminal lymph
drainage, really the question
you're asking is, how
effectively is my patient
breathing? And that's
always the start, whether
your patient's got asthma
or pneumonia, or whether
your patient has a bad
foot ulcer. Ultimately,
if they're not breathing
effectively, their
lymph system will not be
functioning optimally, no
matter what you do locally.
As we look at vascular flow,
So vascular flow is
an important part.
I think it's not
well understood.
So Dr. Millard was a
student of Dr. Still. He did
his writing in the 20s and
even before. This is from
the book he wrote on the
lymphatics. And his theory
really can be condensed
in this statement that the
lymph system is readily
checked in many ways. The
vessels are pliable and
readily compressed. So lymph
vessels are probably more
pliable than even capillaries.
They're tiny vessels.
They're very thin, and
they're very easily obstructed.
And so as we look at
the design of the lymph
vessel, there's, you know, I
think some people look to
use a lymph pump on the
vessels, right? It's the
features of the vessel, the
wall has smooth muscle and
there's valves, right? So
the idea is if I squish
the vessel, I can move it
past the valves and propulse
it forward. That has been
kind of debunked and is
ultimately unnecessary
because with this smooth
muscle and valves, the smooth
muscle has been shown to
have a peristaltic action.
So the contraction, this
is my lymph capillary.
Here's that first valve.
Now I'm in the vessel.
And then as I move the
vessel, I need to move
centrally. The contraction
will occur distally right
at that first valve.
It starts, and now it's
peristaltic so that it
moves the fluid centrally.
and actually it is self
-sufficient you can generate
enough pressure from this
smooth muscle to pump lymph
from your big toe to your
heart while you're standing
up and so you don't need
external forces to pump
lymph through the vessels
the the lymph will move
through the vessels except
that it can be obstructed
with tissue tension and will
add somatic dysfunction.
This was actually researched,
and they were able
to prove that, yes, if
you raise the pressure
in those places where
the limb vessel is
passing, you can actually
obstruct its flow, which
seems pretty obvious,
but there's your proof.
And so you might think,
okay, now, oh, so to
complete this picture,
there is a pacemaker.
And the question is then, how
do we activate the pacemaker?
And ultimately,
the answer to that,
you know, the
smooth muscle has an
innervation. So is it
electrically done? Am I
triggering it with
a sympathetic pulse?
Or am I activating
stretch receptors to
trigger it? So that
would be the mechanical.
The innervation
would be electrical.
And as it turns out,
the sympathetic
nerves will cause
a smooth muscle to contract.
But if I stimulate
the nerve coming here,
it'll go in all
directions. It won't.
And there's no real nerve
node like an SA node
or anything to bring
that innervation in to
the place where it would
stimulate a peristaltic
wave. It doesn't create
a peristaltic wave.
And it's actually not
a very strong pulse.
What it turns out is that
if you fill the lymph,
there are stretch
receptors that will create
that peristaltic action.
And so this was the
best study. They studied this
because they were looking
for a lymph pill and they
thought, oh, I can get
an autonomic, you know, a
sympathomimetic and that'll
be my lymph pill and I can
improve lymph pumping. And
it was obviously
unsuccessful because in your
pharmacology in medicine
classes, you will not learn about
the lymph pump pill because
he did a study where he
really looked at both
electrical and mechanical. And
what he found was without
filling, without mechanically
stimulating, that there's
no pacemaker activity.
And that if you fill,
you'll actually trigger both
mechanical and electrical.
And so really what causes
lymph to propulse is forming
it. If you form lymph,
you'll trigger that
peristaltic action and you'll
get lymph to propulse. And
so with the innervation,
again, And this is a
good article about that.
And he thought, you know,
actually, you know, it's an
immune modulator. That's why
you bring those nerves to
the lymph system, particularly
in the nodes. There's
a pretty big sympathetic
innervation of the nodes, and
it's an immune modulator,
not so much a propulsant.
And so lymphangion,
the vessel with smooth
muscle and valves, has
a peristaltic activity,
can account for all
the movement through
the vasculature, and
dependent on formation.
And interestingly, the
researchers who studied lymph
the most thought lymph
formation was the limiting
factor of the whole system,
partly for this reason.
And so going back
to that concept from
Millard, that the
vessels are pliable
and easily compressed
by tissue strain.
And so it's not
as if you have to
look at every
millimeter of the lymph.
Actually, there really
are key areas, what we'll
call bottlenecks, you
know, where those vessels
have to move through very
tight spaces where dysfunction
is going to be most
consequential. And that's
really where you're going
to find lymph obstructed
in those key areas. And
again, looking at Dr.
Bletschmidt's work, the
embryologist, he tied them,
these areas of congestion
or bottlenecks as being
the areas that that
bottlenecking is actually,
and backup is what causes
the lymph nodes to form.
And so if you want to find
the areas most likely to
be obstructed, it's the
areas where you find all of
the nodes. And like he says,
where the head and neck
meet, where the neck meets
the trunk, and then where
the limbs join the trunk.
And those are going to
be the critical areas. So
here where the head meets
the neck, this area, it's
basically right outside
of the transverse process
of C1 between the mastoid
process and the angle of
the jaw right in that area.
Boy, that is a critical area
for head and neck drainage.
Upper respiratory
infections, you'll find that
totally congested and
dysfunctional. Where the neck meets
the trunk, this is something
that can not only do all
of head and neck drainage,
but really because it's the
inlet, can obstruct lymph
all the way back anywhere.
and as you see this drainage
from the head and neck
coming down, look at how
close it is to the clavicle.
And so, yes, it's the inlet
as a whole, but don't forget
to look at the clavicle
as part of the inlet. It's
not just the first rib and
cervical thoracic junction.
That's an important
thing to look at.
As we're looking at the
upper extremity and chest
wall, the breast, that's
going to come in through the
axilla again where all the
nodes are and tucking under
the axillary fold that can
be an area where it gets
congested particularly pec
minor here which is the
tightest spot through the
axillary fold and then maybe
even more importantly the
space between the clavicle
and first rib that costo
clavicular area a critical
area to look at as we look
at the lower extremity.
There's some opportunity
for obstruction through
the knee. You can see
all the popliteal nodes
forming there, coming in
through the two heads of
gastroc and out between the
two heads of the hamstrings.
You can get obstruction
there, but most of
it is going to be here
at the hip in the femoral
triangle with the roof
of the inguinal ligament,
floor of the iliopsoas
tendon right over the hip.
And then if we're
looking at the viscera,
heart and lungs are
going to drain into the
mediastinum, and
mediastinal fascia will
be a place where you
can find obstruction.
And then if we're looking
at the gut tube through
the mesenteries, and particularly
where the mesenteries
meet the body wall,
that's a place you can get
lymph obstruction. So anywhere
that you're looking at
drainage from, whether
it's visceral inflammation,
extremity inflammation, head
and neck, there's always
going to be critical
areas to look at those
bottlenecking. And then
this place, again, that idea
that the cruise can maybe
effectively be a pump in
healthy function, but if
that diaphragm locks down,
that can obstruct lymph
through the entire belly and
lower extremities. And
that is a critical place.
And then finally, back
to the thoracic inlet,
that crowded area where
not only can head and
neck drainage be
obstructed as it comes down
right here behind the
clavicle coming out and
in relation to the
first rib, but generally
that thoracic duct
drainage itself can be
obstructed and backed up
really in all directions.
And again, in terms of how
this can drive our exam is
that if lymph does obstruct
in any of these areas,
there's a very palpable
congestion, something that you can
really easily find in an
osteopathic exam if you can
expand your examination
beyond tension and stiffness.
and look for congestion.
And you can track that.
So you're looking at
a patient, let's say,
with a big swollen ankle
or foot, and you come
up and you look at the
popliteal space, and
that's all congested.
And you come up to the
femoral triangle, and
this is all congested. And
the hip is all locked
up in psoas and spasm.
And then you come up
here and you don't
find much. and
the thoracic inlet
is normal, no
congestion there at all,
well then you know it's
obstructed down
here at the hip.
And you can find the critical
area of obstruction by
seeing where congestion
occurs and then where it ends.
And in that badly swollen
foot, if it's bad enough,
you should have congestion
all the way up inlet.
And so learning to do that
quick exam, it's a super
quick exam, can be really
telling. And then finally, we
have lymph formation. Again,
that idea that it doesn't
occur by itself. There's
no driving force, intrinsic
driving force for lymph
formation. It's actually
um um an uphill gradient
to get fluid from the
initial lymphatic into the
um from the interstitium
into that initial lymphatic
uh and so um looking
then at the forces
that do that I've spent
some time talking about
fluid fluctuation and I do
believe that fluid
fluctuation is a part of it.
And that's really one
of the ones that we
can really evaluate,
and we're the only ones
who can evaluate it.
There really are a
number of things that
can cause lymph to form.
So
So looking at the design
so we can understand
what sort of forces can
possibly cause lymph
to form, there are two
critical anatomical
factors in the initial
lymph. So this would be
the interstitium.
These are the lymphatic
capillaries, showing them
in two different states.
And so one feature are these,
these little specules here.
Those are called anchoring
filaments. And as you can
see, those anchoring filaments
are tethered into the
interstitium, the collagen
of the interstitium. So as
the interstitium moves, so
will this lymph capillary.
and the other feature
are these endothelial
cells where they meet so
you can see there's no
tight junctions and so
this would be the tight
junction just holding
the the thing together
there's there's no tight
junctions here and so
that's why protein can
move in and out but also
notice that these cells in
this closed position, these
cells actually overlap.
And so that essentially
forms a valve. So if I
can get fluid to move in,
I can trap it and keep
it from moving back out.
So how do we put this
together and make it work?
Well, remember what I
need to do is produce a
pressure gradient. I don't
have an average positive
pressure gradient to move
fluid into the lymph.
What I need to produce
is a temporary pressure
gradient. So look at the
difference in size, right? So
as I draw this open, I'll
reduce the volume here,
which is actually going
to lower the pressure or
I'm going to increase the
volume. I'm sorry, increase
the volume. So I'll lower
the pressure. So let's
say this is the lung. So
this would be the lung at
full inhalation. And as I
inhale, I expand my lung.
I stretch open this lymph.
I lower the pressure
and fluid and whatever
else is there will pour in.
As I breathe out, I'll close
this lymphatic. that'll
increase the pressure
because I have a smaller
volume, the valve closes
and the fluid moves forward.
And so alternating
tissue movements
can also be very effective
formers of lymph. And
the lymphatic system
has adapted itself
to utilize that force
almost everywhere in
the body. So as we look
through, the lungs is
the example I gave you.
As I breathe in, I open the
lymph, I lower the pressure,
I draw fluid in.
As I breathe out, it
collapses, the valve kicks in,
I propel the fluid forward
past that first valve,
activating the stretch
receptor, creating a
peristaltic action. If I
look at the gut tube, what
moves lymph through the
gut tube? Well, two things,
breathing, specifically
the movement
of the diaphragm, and
peristalsis. So in
the gut tube, this
would be at rest.
And then with peristalsis
or the downward movement
of the diaphragm
compressing, I'll close it,
propulse it forward.
As those relax during
exhalation, I'll open the lymph
and draw fluid in. So
peristalsis and breathing.
So looking at this
picture, let's think
about a patient who has
a ruptured appendix.
Well, in those first few
days or sometimes more
after that ruptured appendix,
they have no peristalsis,
and their breathing
is really shallow and
limited, and so they have
this massive inflammatory
process, and they've lost
their lymph pump, and you'll
find this in a lot of
places, in the lungs. with
asthma or pneumonia, the
excursion of the thorax
is diminished. And so
again, a lot of inflammation
and reduced lymph pump.
In skeletal muscle, as
in our extremities, in
our tissues, it's phasic
contraction of the skeletal
muscle that can actually
work to produce lymph.
And again, what happens when
I have a sprained ankle?
I put it in a boot and I keep
off it. So all the things
that would move the lymph
in that also become limited.
And so lots of opportunities
for osteopathic intervention.
And then going back to
that concept of fluid
fluctuation, that as a fluid
wave moves across, at the
peak of that wave, I have a
positive pressure, which will
push fluid right in through
that open cell. And then
the valve won't
allow it to back out.
Think of standing at
the beach, you know, the
wave hits you and it knocks
you up towards shore.
And that would be the peak,
that would be the positive
pressure. And then as the
trough of that wave hits,
that would be like the undertow,
that would be that wave
coming back and pulling you
back out into the ocean.
So as that would happen,
as the trough crosses, and
the valve would effectively
stop that. And so tissue
movement and fluid fluctuation
are the drivers of limb
formation, fluid fluctuation
also being the driver of
interstitial exchange.
And they haven't found that
as much. They've really
studied tissue motion more,
quite honestly. But looking
at the movement of the
arteries, you know, pulse
and something called
arteriolar vasomotion, which is
a slow alternation and
peripheral resistance, actually
can produce a fluid wave.
And the lymphatics also
follow the arterial stream
to take advantage of that.
And so that concept of
fluid fluctuation that
Dr. Sutherland brought
to us, I think is not
just limited to the
cerebrospinal fluid. It's
critical for all the
fluids of our body and
really is tied to one
of the most fundamental
physiologic processes
that occurs in our body.
And so looking at lymph
formation, this is not
an automatic process.
There's actually an
uphill pressure gradient
that has to be overcome
for fluid to move into
an initial lymphatic
because propulsion of
lymph through the vessel
is triggered by lymph
formation. It really
may be the critical
factor in lymph flow.
It requires external forces.
And so this is where we
really should be utilizing
our lymph pump, not trying
to squeeze the vessels
to push the fluid forward,
but actually trying to
assist in the movement.
And so our lymph pump goes
from macroscopic to
microscopic, essentially, and
really should reflect that.
It's a delicate process.
And there was a study,
they did a study on lymph
pumping, where they basically
took an inflamed sheep's
foot and put a cuff, like
a blood pressure cuff,
to pump over the the calf.
So in the area of the
vessels draining the foot,
and that actually did
not improve lymph drainage.
And then right over the
foot where the lymph was
forming, that was what
worked. And that's an
excellent study to sort of kind
of give you some background
as you think about
what you want to do with
your lymph pump techniques.
So as we look at the
lymph, we come to an
important concept in
osteopathy, something that Dr.
Sutherland summed up by
saying that the science of
osteopathy is simple. You
realize you're a mechanic
of the fluids of the body,
as well as of the skeletal
system. And hopefully this
talk opens some avenues
of thinking for you beyond
what you can do to just
make your patient more
comfortable or more mobile.
Learning to manage fluids
really brings you to
the heart of so many
diseases and is so critical.
And so Dr. Still, who
never minced words said,
your patients better pass
you by as a failure until
you are qualified to
deal with the lymphatics.
So I really tried to start
this talk by exploring the
role of the lymph, both in
the interstitium and that
outsized role in inflammation,
and then take you through
the the mechanics of the
lymph system, how it works,
so you can effectively make
a diagnosis and treatment.
And that's it.